Correct. Exactly. Good.
Didn't רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik think that all of כשרות kashrut in
Boston was completely corrupt and he tried to...
Well, everything is corrupt. That's the whole problem with so much of
the כשרות kashrut world and we have to... That's why we have
organizations, but then it's also we have to make sure that the
organizations have checks and
balances and oversight and all sorts of things.
It's a very complicated issue. Okay. Today is ח' אדר, 8th of
Adar, it's February 23rd. Dan Margulis is filling in for רב לינזר
Rabbi Linzer and we will pick up on ל"ח עמוד ב'. lamed
chet amud bet. מיכל Michal told me about ten lines from the
bottom where it says שתיתא, shetita, yeah? So שתיתא, shetita, רש"י Rashi
says: תבשיל העשוי מקמח של קליות, tavshil ha'asui mikemach shel klayot, it's
made out of toasted wheat which has been ground into a flour.
If you toast the wheat first, you denature the gluten so that
when you make it into a porridge it doesn't get so sticky.
So that's why they would do that. שיבשן בתנור she-yavshan b'tanur and
then they dry out the grains. ויש שעושין אותו מקמח עדשים. v'yesh
she-osin oto mikemach adashim. So there were sometimes you make it with
wheat flour and sometimes they made it with lentil flour. וטלפחי מתוקין
יותר מדאי נותן שם חומץ. v'talfache metukim yoter midai noten sham chometz.
So the lentils, which have more sugars in them, I guess fresh
lentils, they add vinegar to balance out the flavor. And that's going
to be the question. Basically the question, the כשרות kashrut question, we're
not really talking about a בישול עכו"ם bishul akum question with this
dish, but we are going to be talking about a חומץ chometz
question. Okay, so שתיתא. shetita. רב שרי, Rav shari, רב Rav said
it's permissible, אבוה דשמואל ולוי אסרי. Avuha d'Shmuel v'Levi asri. And לוי
Levi and the father of שמואל Shmuel both prohibited it. So בחיטי
ושערי כולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי. b'chite v'se'are kulei alma lo pligi
d'shari. Everyone agrees this is going to be our first attempt. Everyone
agrees that those which when it's made with wheat and barley, כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, kulei alma lo pligi d'shari, everyone agrees that
it's permissible. וטלפחי דחלא כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסיר. v'talfache d'chala kulei
alma lo pligi d'asir. And everyone agrees that if it's made with
lentils into which they added vinegar, obviously it should be prohibited because
it has non-kosher vinegar in it. כי פליגי בטלפחי דמיא, ki pligi
b'talfache d'maya, but they disagree about a case where it was made
with lentils, but which it was made with lentils, it was made
lentils with water, not lentils with vinegar. מר סבר גזרינן הא אטו
הא, mar savar gazrinan ha atu ha, so some say we... that
is, אבוה דשמואל Avuha d'Shmuel and לוי Levi say there's a rabbinic
decree against eating this dish which even if you know for sure
it was prepared with water only because we're concerned that you'll come
to interchange it or intermix it with the one that's prepared with
wine vinegar. ומר סבר לא גזרינן u'mar savar lo gazrinan and רב
Rav says לא גזרינן, lo gazrinan, we don't make a גזירה gezeira
in this case.
Wait, but why do we say this is like, you know, גזירה
לגזירה? gezeira l'gezeira?
Exactly. That's the question and that's probably why רב Rav thinks you
shouldn't make such a גזירה, gezeira, because the prohibition of the חומץ
chometz to begin with is an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, is a
גזירה... gezeira... because it's not עבודה זרה avodah zarah wine, it's just
non-Jewish wine, סתם יינם. stam yeinam. So the problem will be do
we make a גזירה gezeira telling you don't even eat the one
made with water to avoid eating the one made with vinegar.
But Rav, so why isn't it a גזירה לגזירה? gezeira l'gezeira? אלא
כולה חד גזירה היא. ela kulo chad gezeira hi.
Well, that's exactly part of the... but it's not כולה חד גזירה
היא kulo chad gezeira hi because clear... clearly here one גזירה gezeira
is about can you eat a dish that you're worried has wine
vinegar in it, which doesn't seem to be part of the consideration.
Right, then why would anyone say it's אסור?
assur? Well, so maybe they disagree about the parameters of how לא
אטו רבנן למגזר גזירה לגזירה lo atu rabbanan l'migzar gezeira l'gezeira or
not, like maybe, you know, maybe that was a debated principle early
on in the period of the אמוראים. Amoraim.
On פסח Pesach the אשכנזים Ashkenazim prohibit eating, you know, any cakes
made of קטניות, kitniyot, right? Because they're concerned that might...
might some... so that's maybe something else, but that's a practice that
developed out of a concern that maybe there'll be חמץ chametz in
it or whatever, but that's not a real formal גזירה, gezeira, that's...
it was a מנהג minhag that developed that was, right. But okay.
Okay. Okay, מר סבר גזרינן הא אטו הא ומר סבר לא גזרינן.
mar savar gazrinan ha atu ha u'mar savar lo gazrinan. ואיכא דאמרי,
v'ika d'amri, second version of the same debate: ואיכא דאמרי בטלפחי דמיא
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסיר. v'ika d'amri b'talfache d'maya kulei alma lo
pligi d'asir. Everyone agrees that when it's lentils prepared with water, it's
prohibited because of this reason that they would have made a rabbinic
law, don't eat this because there's a risk that you'll come to
mix it up with the one that has vinegar in it. כי
פליגי בחיטי ושערי, ki pligi b'chite se'are, but they disagree about a
case where it has either wheat or barley or it's made of
wheat or barley. מר סבר גזרינן הא אטו הא, mar savar gazrinan
ha atu ha, and some say we extend the גזירה gezeira even
further, ומר סבר לא גזרינן, u'mar savar lo gazrinan, and רב Rav
thinks we don't extend the גזירה gezeira even further. So this sounds
like perhaps if this is the issue, then maybe it's more of
a question about some kind of בישול עכו"ם bishul akum question. Maybe
the lentil one is not considered עולה על שולחן מלכים oleh al
shulchan melachim and maybe the one prepared with wheat maybe is, or
something like that, such that there would be more of a problem
of a concern of בישול עכו"ם bishul akum maybe, or maybe it
still is a question of the wine but it's how far do
we extend the concern, the risk of the wine. אמר רב... amar
Rav... Okay, רב Rav said: תרי... trei... two different kinds of שתיטא
*shtita* שדר ברזילי הגלעדי לדוד *shadar
Barzilai HaGiladi l’Dovid*. ברזילי *Barzilai* from גלעד *Gilad*. ברזילי הגלעדי *Barzilai HaGiladi*
is a character in שמואל Shmuel? ב *Shmuel Bais* and he gave
him two different kinds of this porridge to דוד *Dovid*. So this
is just like a little אגדתא *Agadata* and not even sure if
it counts as
אגדתא *Agadata* דכתיב משכב וספות וכלי יוצר חטים ושערים וקמח וקלי ופול
ועדשים וקלי *d’chtiv mishkav vesapot vecholi yotzer chitim use’orim vekemach vekali
upol va’adashim vekali*. So it says וקלי *vekali* twice in the same
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. It must be קליות *klayot*, one kind of קליות
*klayot* made of wheat and one kind of קליות *klayot* made of
lentils. Okay. והשתא דקא מפקא ציני ציני לשוקא דנהרדעא *v’hashta d’ka mapki
tzini tzini l’shuka d’Nehardea* and now people bring out baskets and trays
and trays of this שתיטא *shtita* into the שוק *shuk* of נהרדעא
*Nehardea*. Why is it important that it’s נהרדעא *Nehardea*? Because we said
it was אבוה דשמואל *Avua d’Shmuel* who thought that it was prohibited,
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel's* father. So already by the time of רב *Rav's*
time, a generation later when שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* had taken over for
his father or even after שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, ולית דחייש להא דאבוה
דשמואל ולוי *v’leit d’chaish l’ha d’Avua d’Shmuel v’Levi*. And no one holds
by this חומרא *chumra* to be...
okay. So no one was concerned for their opinion anymore once רב
*Rav* came and said it was permissible even in נהרדעא *Nehardea*, which
was אבוה דשמואל *Avua d’Shmuel's* place. He was the מרא דאתרא *Mar
d’Atra*, nonetheless they didn’t follow his opinion anymore. Okay, we’re on the
third to the last line of ל"ח עמוד ב *Lamed-Chet Amud Bet*.
וכבשים שדרכן לתת לתוכן יין *U-chvashim she-darkan litten betochan yayin*. So what
about pickles that are it’s common to put wine into the into
them, בתוכן יין *betochan yayin*, that is maybe not necessarily wine but
maybe wine vinegar in the production of the pickles. So אמר חזקיה
לא שנו אלא שדרכן *Amar Chizkiyah lo shanu ella she-darkan*. They only
said this הלכה halacha *halacha*, that is that they’re prohibited, in a
place where if it it was customary, it’s normal to do that.
אבל בידוע *Aval beyadu’a*, if you really know that these pickles for
sure are ones that are made with with wine, אסור assur? אפילו
בהנאה *assur afilu behana’ah*. That is our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* is listing
things which are אסור באכילה assur ba'achilah, *assur ba’achilah*, prohibited to be
eaten but not prohibited בהנאה *behana’ah*, but if you know for sure
that it does have wine vinegar in it, not just that it’s
a risk but that you actually know, then it’s not only prohibited
to eat it, it’s even prohibited בהנאה *behana’ah*. That is you wouldn’t
be allowed to sell it or or have a shop making it
or something like that. ומאי שנא ממורייס *U-mai shena mi-muryas*?
So why is it different than מורייס moryas *muryas*
דשרו רבנן rabbanan. בהנאה *d’sharu rabbanan behana’ah*, that the רבנן *Rabbanan* permitted
the מורייס moryas, *muryas* that you’re allowed to get הנאה *hana’ah* from
מורייס moryas *muryas*. התם לעבורי זוהמא *Hatam le-avurei zuhama*.
In the מורייס muryas *muryas* production they add wine or wine vinegar
into the fish brine in order to to remove the stink of
the fish. So it’s to take away something bad. הכא למתוקי טעמא
*Hacha le-matukei ta’ama*. But here the wine is added to sweeten the
pickles. So there’s a different role being played. If it’s to remove
a bad taste or if it’s to add a good taste, those
are considered different in this הלכה halakha *halacha* at least. Why? Maybe
the sense is...
even if it’s עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* wine or whatever, who
cares why I’m adding it? So maybe it’s not עבודה זרה *Avodah
Zarah* wine, it’s only it’s it’s דרבנן *d’rabbanan*.
So all of this is about דינים דרבנן *dinim d’rabbanan*, and the
sense was if it’s an ingredient that’s added only sort of to
take away a bad taste, to cover up a bad taste or
a bad smell, that’s not the level of of ingredient that we
would be so concerned with. Maybe it’s more בטל batel? *batel*. But
if it’s really... maybe it’s already בטל ברוב *batel berov* and we
haven’t seen that argument yet. But I’m just saying that what’s here...
so this is what it’s saying. The difference between מורייס *muryas* and
pickles is that in מורייס *muryas* you put it in to cover
up the fish stink and in the pickles you add it to
actually flavor the pickles, so there it’s adding more of
a positive to cover up the whatever stink versus flavor for the
taste of it. If I’m adding the same amount, who cares why
I’m adding it?
So maybe there is a difference. At least for דינים דרבנן *dinim
d’rabbanan*, maybe they created this distinction. Maybe I don’t understand. Okay, it’s
that’s I’m just reading the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, that’s what it
says in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Okay. ורבי יוחנן *ve-Rabbi Yochanan*...
is that still part of the...
I don’t know any I don’t know any real application of that
principle besides this kind of a case. The thing that does come
to mind is the difference of proportions, meaning when you have something
that’s like a דבר המעמיד *davar ha-ma’amid* or מילתא דעבידא לטעמא *milta
d’avida l’ta’ama*, things that have a strong taste or are added in
as flavorings or are added in as binders and things like that,
very often the sense is that the הלכה halakha *halacha* should be
that those would be not בטל *batel* even in a minute quantity
because they are added to serve a certain constructive production purpose.
But in that case... so that’s the difference there for those things.
I’m sorry, I’m just too distracted by the baby. Okay. Okay. Then
you come with אבא. She sure doesn't want. Okay. Okay.
She's fine.
Okay. Okay.
Figure out how to put this on.
One second. Sorry for the delay. Okay. Yay. Okay.
Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו בידוע נמי מותר. Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu
beyadu nami mutar. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even if you
know that it's there, that is that you know that these pickles
regularly have the wine vinegar in them, it's still permissible. ומאי שנא
מורייס לרבי מאיר דאסר בהנאה? U-maishnai moryas lerabbi meir de'assar behana'ah? So
how is it different than the מורייס which רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah because it could have
wine in it?
Okay. התם ידיע ממשו הכא לא ידיע ממשן. Hatam yedia mamasho hacha
lo yedia mamashan.
So basically the difference is in
regarding ביטול. bitul. If you look at the top רש"י: Rashi: וידוע
ממשו שהרי מטבילין בו והרוטב נאכל והיין נאכל עמו. Veyadua mamasho sheharei
matbilin bo veharotav ne'echal vehayayin ne'echal imo. That is the ממשן. mamashan.
Do you actually use the pickle juice for anything? So the מורייס,
because the מורייס is produced as a sauce, as a flavoring, then
even the wine that's added into it is going to be eaten
itself.
When you have the pickles,
the pickles are flavored by the wine, but the ממש, mamash, the
actual wine itself is not being consumed because nobody drinks the pickle
juice, they just eat the pickles themselves.
It's still being flavored by it.
Right, so they're אסור באכילה, assur ba'achilah. but they're not אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah because they don't have the ממש mamash of the wine
absorbed into them. So this is also an interesting question of how
do we consider the taste? Maybe even the taste of something which
is אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah is not itself אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
it only remains אסור באכילה. asur b'achilah So that's an interesting question
which comes out of this. Okay, we are at the top of
ל"ט עמוד א' Lamed tet amud aleph and the second line.
וטרית טרופה, U-trit trufa, chopped fish, וציר שאין בו דג, Vetzir she'ein
bo dag, and the fish brine that does not have any fish
in it. So now we're going to see an extensive discussion of
the different rules of fish כשרות kashrut questions
that come up here. The main principle in כשרות kashrut of fish
is articulated in נדה Niddah as well as in חולין, Chullin, I
think, which is that the תורה Torah gives two different כשרות kashrut
signs for a fish: כל שיש לו סנפיר וקשקשת. kol sheyesh lo
snapir vekaskeses. What's a סנפיר? snapir?
A fin. And what's a קשקשת? kaskeses? Scales. It's interesting it's in
the singular, so if even if you have only one scale.
But leads to all sorts of interesting questions. Charlie is grinning.
Well it can just have one fin also.
Well you could have one fin and one scale. So first of
all the גמרא Gemara. gives us a principle that כל שיש לו
קשקשת יש לו סנפיר. kol sheyesh lo kaskeses yesh lo snapir. If
you have קשקשת, kaskeses, if you have scales, then it also has
fins, so you really only need to know whether the fish has
scales or not. And secondly,
יש לו סנפיר אין לו קשקשת. yesh lo snapir ein lo kaskeses.
There are fish which have the appropriate kind of fins but do
not have scales. And therefore it doesn't actually do you anything to
check if the fish has a fin. What that does is it
actually makes it easier to identify what's a kosher fish or not
because you could just look at the skin. Look at the fish's
skin and you can see whether it's kosher or not.
But it's more than just having scales like you know like let's
say how big the
scales, like you can ignore them, do they come off? These kind
of the question of whether fish with have scales, temporary scales or
scales that come off is exactly on our דף. daf. Just one
other piece of information which is interesting we're going to see is
a discussion of invertebrate fish. It seems the assumption חז"ל Chazal had
was that there are no invertebrate fish which are kosher, which is
sort of the general rule that we have. The problem of course
is how do you determine what's a fish and what's not even
a fish at all? So what about something like a sea cucumber
or a coral or barnacles or clams and things? Coral, I don't
know, there you could eat the coral have
the polyps. You
do know the word for
it, I figured it out. Right. So I think one of the
early reform arguments actually for, you know, this is sort of back
before reform totally threw out any kind of הלכתי halachic process, they
were still trying to make arguments to defend and I think it
was Isaac Mayer Wise even said something about so he tried to
say that oysters were not a fish according to הלכה halakha but
actually that oysters are a rock that happens to have food inside
because they don't move, they just sit there, they look like rocks.
So that goes to also the question of קשקשת, kaskeses, is the
shell of a shellfish a single scale that protects the animal? So
these are obviously questions that the פוסקים poskim have dealt with, but
it's interesting. consider. Okay, so my חילק. chilek. So first of all,
we have to go back to what we talked about a few
days ago, which is the חילק, chilek, the fish that's left over
after the production of the מוריאס muryas is called in Latin Halex,
and that's what we're talking about here. So what is this fish?
So what kind of fish was it produced from? That is, if
you go and buy, I'm going to get a big sack of,
you know, fish parts to spread and put in my porridge, is
it going to be a kosher fish or not? אמר רב נחמן
בר אבא אמר רב, Amar Rav Nachman bar Abba Amar Rav, זו
סולתנית. Zo Sultanit. It is a Sultanit fish. ומפני מה אסרוה? U-mipnei
mah asruha? מפני שארבונא עולה עמה. Mipnei she-arvona olah imah. The Sultanit
is a kosher fish, I think it's some kind of a mackerel
or something like that.
They say, they're not sure, it's- some say it might be a
type of sardine.
Sardine, right, it's in the Mediterranean, sardine is probably a good guess.
Because you know what it says it develops
its scales only when it matures. Well, we're going to see that's
in the next סוגיא. sugya. Oh. So the problem of getting this
חילק chilek from a source that you're not sure is not that
the fish itself, the main fish, will be a problem, but that
when the non-Jewish fisherman catch this fish, ארבונא עולה עמה. arvona olah
imah. There's a whole multitude of other fish that get caught in
the nets together, and they don't care whether they have kosher fish
or non-kosher fish, so they dump them all in and then it's
going to have a mixture.
That's true for basically all wild caught fish.
It is true for all wild caught fish and then the question
becomes are- oh, but when they're actually processing the fish, like I'm
going to buy a piece of salmon, I still have the skin
on the salmon or whether I know...
It must be from a fish farm.
Well, but wild salmon or whatever, but meaning the questions of tuna,
the question- right, and there were the questions especially with these kind
of nets. Do they catch dolphins in the tuna or not? Is
it a מיעוטא mi'uta that's a real חשש, chashash, you know, is
it one in sixty? Right, will the dolphin be בטל? Now thankfully
they have the dolphin-free nets anyway which do a much better job,
but these are at least important interesting questions. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan.
Basically we're saying because most likely there's non-kosher fish.
Yeah.
There could be a concern, there's a risk that it will contain
the non-kosher fish.
And what's this word? What does ארבונא arvona mean? Non-kosher fish?
No, it's not a type of non-kosher- it's that the- a mixture.
ערבוביא Arvuvia basically, right? Like a
mixture? וגם הערבונא זכור לטוב. V'gam ha-arvona zachur latov. Arvona. Right, I
don't know. Okay. עולה עמה. Olah imah. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So
now this is a סוגיא sugya which- which has parallel in חולין
Chullin as well, but we're learning it here so when we get
to חולין, Chullin, we'll have already learned it. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
אין לו עכשיו ועתיד לגדל לאחר זמן. Ein lo achshav ve-atid legadel
le-achar zman. What if it does not have scales right now but
it will grow the scales in the future? Okay? כגון הסולתנית והאפיץ.
Kegon ha-Sultanit ve-ha-Afitz. These two different types of fish, Sultanit and Afitz,
they do not currently- they in their juvenile phase of development do
not have scales and then they grow the scales later. הרי זה
מותר. Harei zeh mutar. That's permissible. That is, the fish does not
have to retain the scales it- or- or have scales for its
entire life cycle in order to be kosher. יש לו עכשיו ועתיד
להשיר. Yesh lo achshav ve-atid le-hashir. So if it has scales now
but the scales fall off later, which is the opposite problem. בשעה
שעולה מן הים. Besha'ah she-olah min hayam. They fall off- מן הים
min hayam when the scales fall off when it gets out of
the water. כגון אקונס ואפונס. Kegon akunas ve-afunas.
Other types of fish. וכתפסתיס ואכפסתיס
ואותינס. V'katpastis v'achpastis v'otinas. אותינס, Otinas, I think is pretty clear that
it is tuna. But all of the other fish...
Here they say, this is interesting. What? They define this. So אקונס
Akunas is some sort of mackerel. Okay. So that would be one
that's מותר. mutar. Then the other, I can't even pronounce it. It's
אכטפיא? achtapia? Here they say it's a swordfish.
Well, swordfish is a matter of large amount of debate among the
פוסקים poskim about whether or not the type of scales that swordfish
has are or not kosher and whether the part of the fish's
development they do or do not have the scales and do they
fall off... It says it's kosher though, מותר. mutar. So certainly there
are many of those who think it is kosher and there are
even I think going back to Marc Shapiro, Marc Shapiro showed me
there's a
19th-century advertisement from the Lower East Side delis, kosher delis, all in
יידיש, Yiddish, they'd say we have salmon, we have herring, we have
this, we have swordfish, like all... so there certainly was a time
when swordfish was considered to be kosher by many communities. There have
been a major debate in the 20th century among many פוסקים poskim
about whether or not the type of scales that the swordfish has
qualify as קשקשת kaskeset or not. Rabbi Tendler was very involved in
this.
So they- so they have a different
definition of this?
I assume they do. It says מותר.
mutar. Right. Well, so obviously whatever type of fish we're talking about
is מותר mutar and whether we can identify it with a current
species of fish or not is a separate question.
And then אותינס Otinas is tuna.
אותינס Otinas is clearly tuna. Right. Okay. So these fish, the assumption
is that they- they have scales which could fall off when they're
removed from the water. That is the scales are very weakly attached
to the skin and this is something that's actually general rule for
the types of kosher fish is that the scales scrape off easily
without damaging the skin of the fish. So if the scales could
fall off easily, it's a good indication.
scales of a tuna fall off?
The scales of the tuna could fall off relatively easily if you
get a tuna. Swordfish? Swordfish, they fall off or swordfish not necessarily
even have any appreciable scales at all in maturity. And the tuna
regularly the scales can fall off. You know, if you get a
tuna that has the skin on it, you'll see that it doesn't
really feel scaly.
So these, you know, we have we know that they're kosher fish,
we've seen them with the scales, we know, so those are kind
of things. It's about establishing the species.
The big other big question is the sturgeon. Sturgeon and different many
different species of sturgeon have different types of scales and they are
placoid scales and they're cycloid scales and I don't know all the
differences between fish identification. But the הנודע ביהודה Noda B'Yehuda has a
major שאלה shaila because it was very common to use an extract
from the sturgeon in clarifying beer and wine. It's called isinglass. In
יידיש Yiddish it's called הויזן בלוזן, hoizenblozen, which is a hilarious word
to read in a תשובה, teshuva, but the part of the discussion
there is whether the sturgeon is or is not a kosher fish.
Sorry, and I'm correcting myself, the Marc Shapiro thing was not about
swordfish, was about sturgeon. The sturgeon and sturgeon caviar and all these
kind of things were very popular in Eastern Europe and then the
question is, again, is it a kosher type of fish, is it
not? Different communities had different standards. It was a big debate.
But you see, there wasn't the advertisement for kosher swordfish.
As far as I know, not the swordfish. He has other things
about swordfish, but the sturgeon was really...
in Italy they swordfish fish.
In Italy? So the other problem... In Italy they swordfish? The other
problem, and in Israel there are people who eat swordfish.
Wait, can we have it in Italy?
The other problem with swordfish is it's very overfished and it's a
problem, it's an environmental question.
No, the bigger problem is mercury, they've
got really mercury, very high mercury levels. So these are all important
questions as well.
Okay. So רבי אבהו בקיסרי קרבי דגים ועוברים ניקחים מכל אדם. Rabbi
Abbahu be-Keisari kirvei dagim ve-ubarim nikachim mi-kol adam. So Rabbi Abbahu said
in Caesarea, קרבי
דגים, kirvei dagim, the the
you can know the fish
fish guts... ועוברים ניקחים מכל אדם, ve-ubarim nikachim mi-kol adam, you can
buy them from any person. That is, you can go to the
regular market, even where they're non-Jews, and purchase the fish organs. Okay.
Here's someone on the eggs.
ובראנא? u-barana? Oh וברא, u-bara, the roe, the caviar. Okay.
Why? חזקתן אינן באין
אלא מפלסא ואספמיא chazkatan einan ba'in ela mi-pulsa ve-aspamia because we have
a חזקה chazaka that they only come from Pulsa and Spain. כי
הא דאמר אביי האי תכנתא דבב נהרא שריא ki ha de-amar Abaye
hai tachnata de-Bab Nahara sharya because and where they
only have kosher fish.
Right, where they only have kosher fish, right. I forgot to mention
that point. That's the important part. Okay. And it's like Abaye said,
quoting that Abaye said, the Bab River in... it's nice that they
have a Bab River because Bab means the door. It's like flows,
it's the door to, right? So the Bab River, all of the
fish in the Bab River are kosher. מאי טעמא אילימא משום דרדיפי
מיא? mai ta'ama? Ilima mishum de-radifei maya? Maybe you'll say it's because
the water is very strong? והא דג טמא כיון דלית ליה חוט
השדרה ve-ha dag tamei keivan de-leit lei chut ha-shidra because non-kosher fish
are invertebrates, they don't have a spinal column.
Is that true?
Some non-kosher fish are, but not all. Right, so at least the
type that they were concerned of.
Sharks and... ray. Okay. So certain kinds at least are. So because
they don't have a spinal column, because the current is very strong,
בדוכתא דרדיפי מיא לא מצי. be-duchta de-radifei maya la matzi. So the
reason why is because the current is very strong, they won't be
able to survive in that river, so they don't live there. Okay.
והא קחזינא דקאי? ve-ha ka-chazina de-ka'i? But wait a second, there are
such fish who can survive in very fast rivers. דקאי, אלא משום
דמליחי מיא. de-ka'i. Ela mishum de-mali'chi maya. No,
it's because the Bab River has salty water. והא דג טמא כיון
דלית ליה קלפי בדוכתא דמליחי מיא לא מצי
קאי. ve-ha dag tamei keivan de-leit lei kalpei be-duchta de-mali'chi maya la
matzi ka'i. So because they don't have scales. So if they're in
a very salty water, they don't have scales to protect their skin.
Which again, is not true because we know that there are non-kosher
fish who live in the ocean all the time. Okay, so that's
not going to be the reason either. והא קחזינא דקאי, ve-ha ka-chazina
de-ka'i,
but we've seen that there are non-kosher fish who can live in
salty water. אלא משום דלא מרבי טינא, ela mishum de-lo marbei tina,
it's because it has a lot of mud. And the mud, לא
מרבי, lo marbei, they can't reproduce in that mud because they need
to reproduce in a clearer water or they need to have more
less sediment. So לא מרבי טינא דג טמא. lo marbei tina dag
tamei. So the the mud prevents non-kosher fish from spawning there, and
therefore they don't live in that river. Okay. I have a question.
Yeah?
I was going to say, there are actually are river sharks in
India and Southeast Asia.
Well, that's very interesting.
Right, I was going to say something like that.
Right, so the point is, and Rav only said this about a
specific river at a specific time when he was clear, and we're
going to see at later point, אמר רבינא האידנא דקשפכי בה נהר
גוזא ונהר גמדא. amar Ravina, ha'idna de-ka-shafchi beh Nahar Guza ve-Nahar Gamda.
now that they've made canals that the water from these two other
rivers flows into the Bab river, אסירי, asire, it's no longer permissible
because they've all been intermixed.
That is, perhaps Ravina re-examined the reality. So even when you have
a teaching from Rav about a real-life
reality situation, you have to make sure to go out and reassess
and check what the reality is and reconsider. Except when we don't.
Well but we should. Okay, if you're Ravina then you can. Okay.
Or is this only to make something אסור?
assur, It could go both ways. It should go both ways. אמר
אביי האי חמרא דימא שרי, Amar Abaye hai hamra de-yama sharei, de-yama
sharei.
So the donkey of the sea is
permitted.
I know about the chicken of the sea.
So we're talking donkey of the sea. So donkey of the sea
maybe something like a seahorse. I'm not sure. Not really sure. But
whatever kind of fish it was, they called it donkey of the
sea.
You hear in modern Hebrew this חמור הים hamor hayam is used
to refer to cod.
Cod. Okay, well I don't know. Okay, it's not a
seahorse. Certainly not a seahorse. But why is it called this, why
is it cod, because it's ugly? For Atlantic cod?
I don't know.
Anyway, but the point is, right, אמר אביי האי חמרא דימא שרי.
Amar Abaye ha-hamra de-yama sharei. The donkey of the sea is kosher.
תורא דימא, Tora de-yama, but the ox of the sea, the right,
they didn't have chicken of the sea, they had cow of the
sea, cow of the sea אסיר assir is prohibited. סימנך, Simanach, the
way to remember it, טמא טהור טהור טמא, tamei tahor tahor tamei,
the most confusing סימן. siman. The donkey is kosher and the cow
is not kosher. Okay. אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi:
שפרנונא שרי. shapharnuna sharei. The shapharnuna, the beautiful fish is kosher. קדש
נונא אסיר, Kadesh nuna assir, but the holy fish is prohibited. וסימנך,
ve-simanach, קדוש לה', kadosh l'hashem, the holy one you have to leave
off for God. You're not allowed to eat it as if because
it's קודש. kodesh. It's very interesting. ואיכא דאמרי כבארנונא, ve-ika d'amri kabarnuna,
but there are those who call it kabarnuna. So אסור, that one
is prohibited. וסימנך, ve-simanach, קברי עובדי כוכבים, kivrei ovdei kochavim, the graves
of idolaters, the graves of non-Jews are prohibited because graves are prohibited
also just to get any benefit from. So if it's called kabarnuna,
that kind of fish is not permitted. Okay. Basically they're just telling
you which are the kosher fish and which are not. Obviously we
know the סימן siman and you should go investigate nowadays all the
different types of fish. There's a מצוה, mitzvah, the רמב"ם Rambam counts
it as a separate מצוה mitzvah for each of mammals, birds, fish,
and locust, each one of those a separate מצוה, mitzvah, four different
מצוות mitzvot in the תורה, Torah, to know and apply
the kosher signs of those animals. That is, we should be studying
these הלכות halachot to be aware of the different species. We should
study the fish and the birds and everything to understand their different
taxonomy and how they're related to each other and how they interbreed
and all these sorts of things and we're fulfilling a מצוה mitzvah
when we do that. So it's wonderful, it's an opportunity where we
do תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, where we actually are doing two different
מצוות mitzvot at once. Okay.
Does that mean that he actually knew what these things were or
this was aspirational? Who? The רמב"ם. Rambam.
Presumably every person who studies kosher fish should go out and research
in their area which are the kosher fish, which are the non-kosher
fish, what do they look like, what are the different species. You
have to go get a ichthyologist.
Yeah, the fish industry is really corrupt.
It's very corrupt. There's a lot of concern now, Charlie's talking about,
it's become a very big problem, concern especially with the white fishes
in particular, things like cod and flounder and halibut and all these
sorts of things that are kosher species, but there is a concern
in many fish markets that they interchange different species of fish, cheaper
fish which you can get from wherever for the more expensive, more
desirable fish and most people can't tell the difference. The problem is
what if they're using a non-kosher species of fish in replacement of
a kosher species and you don't know? And the general requirement and
the general rule even going back to שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and
from the גמרא is not to buy an unidentified piece of fish
without the skin still on it. So even if you get the
wrong species of kosher fish, at least you make sure that you're
still getting a kosher fish. That's really the rule. And there may
be exceptions. There may be circumstances where because you can identify it
even without the skin, maybe you don't, like salmon, like tuna, even
like other certain kinds of fish, maybe if you know the way
it looks like and how the fish the texture of the fish
and things like that, maybe there's room to rely on that as
well and those are important questions. Okay.
It should be known that catfish is a farm-raised fish that is
very cheap.
Right, catfish is very cheap and catfish is very non-kosher. And catfish
put it down, it should be kosher.
Which? As טמא טהור. tamei tahor.
No, but that's only for those two, only for those two fish.
Okay, it's not a general rule. Okay. The cat of the sea.
The cat of the sea, exactly. Okay. רבי עקיבא איקלע לגינזק. Rabbi
Akiva iklei le-Ginzak. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva went to Ginzak, ואייתו לקמיה
ההוא נונא דהוה
דמי לחיפוצא חפי בדיקולא. ve-aitu le-kamei ha-hu nuna de-havei dami le-hipusa hafi
bi-dikula. So they brought before him this a kind of fish,
okay, that it was like a חיפוצא, hipusa,
which is like a non-kosher fish, חפי בדיקולא, hafi bi-dikula, he put
it into a basket. חזא ביה קלפי ושריוה chaza bei kalpei vesharyei
but he saw once it was in the basket it was he
put it into the water to see and he saw that it
had scales so he permitted it. That is a רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva realized that they confused easily confused a kosher type of fish
and non-kosher type of fish and and he was able to permit
it for them. רב אשי איקלע לתמדוריא. Rav Ashi ikla letamduria. He
רב אשי Rav Ashi went to תמדוריא. Tamduria. אייתו לקמיה ההוא נונא
דהוה דמי לצלוחא. aitu lekamei hahu nuna dehavah dami letslufcha.
They brought him a fish that was similar to the צלוחא tslufcha
fish which is a non-kosher fish. נקטיה להדי יומא חזא דהוה ביה
סימני ושריוה nakteih lahadei yoma chaza dehavah bei simanei vesharyei
and he basically did a similar kind of experiment to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and tested it and saw that it had scales and
it was kosher. רב אשי איקלע לההוא אתרא Rav Ashi ikla lehahu
atra and רב אשי Rav Ashi went to the same place or
a such and such place. It's interesting why it's ההוא אתרא hahu
atra and they don't tell us where. So אייתו לקמיה נונא דהוה
דמי לשפרנונא. aitu lekamei nuna dehavah dami leshafranuna. They brought him out
a fish that looked similar to the שפרנונא shafranuna and we said
שפרנונא shafranuna is not kosher, sorry שפרנונא shafranuna is kosher. חייפי במשכלי
חוירי. chaifei bemashichlei chavirei.
He put it with a white white background. חזא ביה קלפי ושריוה
chaza bei kalpei vesharyei and he saw that it had scales and
he permitted it. רבה בר בר חנה איקלע לאקרא דאגמא. Rabbah bar
bar Chana ikla la'akra de'agma. רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar
Chana went to אקרא דאגמא. Akra de'Agma. קריבו ליה צחנתא. karivu lei
tsachnata. So
they brought him out the צחנתא. tsachnata. שמעיה לההוא גברא shamei lehahu
gavra and
he took it out to this to his friend. דהוה קרי ליה
באטי dehavah karei lei bati sorry they brought him out a צחנתא,
tsachnata, the fish dip, fish broth
and he heard שמעיה לההוא גברא shamei lehahu gavra he heard someone
describing it in the background like the chef or something דהוה קרי
ליה באטי. dehavah karei lei bati. He called it באטי bati and
באטי bati is a non-kosher fish. So he said אמר מדקא קרי
ליה באטי שמע מינה דבר טמא אית ביה. amar deka karei lei
bati shma mina davar tamei it bei.
So he says it must be there's something non-kosher in this fish
broth. לא אכל מיניה lo achal minei and he didn't eat it.
לצפרא letsafra in the morning when he could see better עיין בה.
ayen bah. He investigated. אשכח ביה דבר טמא ashkach bei davar tamei
and he found something that was very obviously non-kosher in it. קרי
אנפשיה kari anafshei and he said about himself the פסוק from משלי
Mishlei לא יאונה לצדיק כל און lo yo'uneh latsadik kol aven that
that it's good to be a צדיק. tsadik. To be a צדיק
tsadik means that you make sure that nothing bad happens. That is
he made sure by being extra careful the night before when he
couldn't investigate he saved himself from sinning. Okay. והכורת של חלתית veha'koret
shel chiltit a sliver, a slice of חלתית. chiltit. What's חלתית? chiltit?
חלתית chiltit seems to be asafoetida. Asafoetida
is a very pungent spice
and we're going to see what the problem is. That is the
problem from our משנה mishna on דף ל"ה עמוד ב'. daf lamed
hey amud bet. It says וכורת של חלתית ומלח של אקונית הרי
אלו אסורים ואין איסורן איסור הנאה. vekoret shel chiltit umelach shel akodnit
harei elu asurim ve'ein isuran isur hana'ah.
So it's אסור באכילה but not איסור הנאה. isur hana'ah. So what's
the problem? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? משום דמפסיק ליה בסכינא. mishum demafsik
lei besakina. They cut it with a knife. Wait so cutting things
with a knife is prohibited? So what's going to be the problem?
So אף על גב דאמר מר נותן טעם לפגם מותר af al
gav de'amar mar noten ta'am lifgam mutar even though the general principle
is that if the taste from the knife will negatively impact the
food then it will be permissible. That is the taste that's transferred
is not a beneficial taste. We say נותן טעם לפגם מותר noten
ta'am lifgam mutar that a detrimental taste is not prohibited. אגב חורפי
דחלתיתא מחליא ליה שמנוניתא. agav churfei dechiltita mechalyah lei shamnunitah.
The spiciness of the חלתיתא chiltita revives מחליא mechalyah it makes it
it makes it stronger the grease of the knife. That is the
concern seems to be that the knife has non-kosher meat grease on
it like lard on it or something like that and the so
even though it would be a detrimental taste for the spice but
we say oh actually the spiciness of the spice
awakens the taste and makes it more beneficial. Okay. והוה ליה כנותן
טעם לשבח vahavei lei kenoten ta'am lishvach
and it's like it gives a beneficial taste ואסור ve'asur and it
should be prohibited. Okay. Okay.
Okay. עבדי דרבי לוי avdei deRabbi Levi the servant of רבי לוי
Rabbi Levi הוה קא מזבין
חלתיתא.
havah ka mazbin
chiltita. כי נח נפשיה דרבי לוי. kinach nafshei deRabbi Levi. Okay so
when רבי לוי Rabbi Levi died one second.
Okay. כי נח נפשיה דרבי לוי אתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. kinach nafshei
deRabbi Levi atu lekamei deRabbi Yochanan.
When רבי לוי Rabbi Levi died they came before רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. אמרי ליה מהו למזבן מיניה? amri lei mahu lemizban minei? Should
we still continue buying from him? אמר להו עבדו של חבר הרי
הוא כחבר. amar lehu avdo shel chaver harei hu kechaver. The slave
of a חבר chaver of a reliable kosher-keeping person is still considered
to be a חבר chaver because that is we might have thought
we should have a less of a reliability for slaves because a
slave... even though they're bound by these מצוות, mitzvot, they're not necessarily
bought into the fullest extent. But to which he responds, actually no,
because he's accustomed to it because he's grown up in this household
and he knows the rules, he could be relied upon. So עבדו
של חבר הרי הוא כחבר. avdo shel chaveir harei hu ke-chaveir. רב
הונא בר מניומי זבן תכלתא מאינשי דביתי Rav Huna bar Manyumi zavan
techeilta me-inshei deveiteih and רב הונא בר מניומי Rav Huna bar Manyumi
bought תכלת techelet from מאינשי דביתי, me-inshei deveiteih, from the people of
his household. It often is a reference to his wife. One second,
and I'm just checking רש״י Rashi about something. I can't find the
רש״י. Rashi. Okay. Anyway, okay. דרב עמרם חסידא. De-Rav Amram Chasida. So
he bought תכלת techelet from the women of רב עמרם חסידא's Rav
Amram Chasida household. אתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, Ato lekamei de-Rav Yosef, they
came to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. לא הוה בידיה. Lo hava beyadeih.
What? אשתו. Ishto. What? The
רש״י. Rashi. Yeah, yeah, מאינשי דביתי, me-inshei deveiteih, right. מאינשי דביתי Me-inshei
deveiteih always you find is a reference to the wife. So they
came to ask רב יוסף Rav Yosef if it's permissible to buy
תכלת techelet from a woman from his household. לא הוה בידיה Lo
hava beyadeih and he didn't have an answer to that question because
the question of on the one hand, a woman not obligated in
ציצית tzitzit and on the other hand that she's אשת חבר, eishet
chaveir, she knows the הלכות halakhot and maybe is there a concern
or not that she's going to have intermixed the תכלת techelet with
an inappropriate blue dyed wool that she didn't know that you were
going to use it for the מצוה mitzvah or something like that.
Okay.
פגע בחנן חייטא, Paga be-Chanan Chayata, he encountered חנן חייטא, Chanan Chayata,
חנן Chanan the
tailor. אמר ליה
יוסף אני אמינא לה בדידי הוה עובדא דזביני תכלתא מאינשי דביתי דרבנן.
Amar lei Yosef ani amina
lah bedidi hava ovda de-zavini techeilta me-inshei deveiteih de-rabbanan. So he says
no, I had this case where I would buy the תכלת techelet
from the women, the wives of רבנן. Okay, okay.
He makes so
much
noise.
Why? Okay, okay. אתאי לקמיה דרב יהודה מהגרוניא, Atai lekamei de-Rav Yehuda
me-Hagrunya, they came before רב יהודה Rav Yehuda from הגרוניא. Hagrunya. אמר
ליה נפקת לך הא דאמר שמואל, Amar lei nafkat lach ha de-amar
Shmuel, have you come across this teaching of שמואל? Shmuel אשת חבר
הרי היא כחבר. Eishet chaveir harei hi ke-chaveir. The wife of a
חבר chaveir is also considered to be like a חבר, chaveir, that
is she also knows the הלכות, halakhot, so you can assume even
if it's a מצוה mitzvah she doesn't keep herself, if you're going
to buy תכלת techelet from her, you're going to buy ציצית tzitzit
from her, that she'll know the הלכה halakha, and will be able
to provide you with a kosher ציצית. tzitzit. Because there was a
problem, the rabbis in the time of the rabbis, there was counterfeit
תכלת. techelet. I meant to explain this. It was made from indigo
called קלא אילן. kala ilan. We'll learn about it when we get
to מסכת מנחות, masechet Menachot,
extensive discussion there. But the rabbis made a rule that you're not
supposed to buy תכלת techelet except from someone who's a reliable trustworthy
person because maybe someone is pulling a fast one, they're selling you
a vegetable dyed strings which are going to be cheaper in order
to save money and therefore you're not going to be יוצא yotzei
the מצוה mitzvah the appropriate way. So in this regard we say
אשת חבר הרי היא כחבר, eishet chaveir harei hi ke-chaveir, that you
could buy it from the wife of this rabbi. You know that
she's providing you with a kosher תכלת. techelet. Okay. Even though she
may not necessarily, so we can assume she does know the הלכות
halakhot of the ציצית, tzitzit, her husband has informed her, even though
she might generally not necessarily know
that.
Okay. I love you,
okay.
Okay.
Okay. דתנו רבנן. De-tanu rabbanan. So שמואל taught this because based on
this ברייתא. baraita. אשת חבר הרי היא כחבר עבדו של חבר הרי
הוא כחבר. Eishet chaveir harei hi ke-chaveir avdo shel chaveir harei hu
ke-chaveir. So שמואל taught it only because it's a ברייתא, baraita, that
is a wife of a חבר chaveir is considered חבר chaveir and
the slave of a חבר chaveir is considered a חבר. chaveir. חבר
שמת, Chaveir she-meit, once a חבר chaveir dies, אשתו בניו ובני ביתו
הרי הן בחזקתם עד שיחשדו. ishto banav u-venei beito harei hen be-chezkatam
ad she-yeichashdu. So once the man of the house dies, everyone in
the household is still assumed to continue to maintain the same level
of הלכה halacha observance until they do something that raises suspicions. וכן
חצר שמוכרין בה תכלת הרי הן בחזקתן עד שתיפסל. Ve-chen chatzer she-mokhrin
bah techeilta harei hen be-chezkatam ad she-tipasel. And also a stall in
the marketplace where they sell
תכלת, techelet,
they remain in their חזקה, chazakah, we can assume we have a
presumption that they're kosher as long as they're still kosher until they
do something that lowers their presumption. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. The first
wide line at the bottom of לט עמוד א. lamed tet amud
alef. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. אשת עם הארץ שניתת לחבר. Eishet am
ha-aretz she-nisat le-chaveir. The wife of an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, of
an ignoramus, of someone who doesn't follow הלכה halacha or is not
well educated in the הלכה, who then is widowed or divorced who
marries a חבר. chaveir. וכן בתו של עם הארץ שניתת לחבר Ve-chen
bito shel am ha-aretz she-nisat le-chaveir or the daughter of an עם
הארץ am ha-aretz who marries a חבר, chaveir, וכן עבדו של עם
הארץ שנמכר לחבר ve-chen avdo shel am ha-aretz she-nimkar le-chaveir or a
slave of an עם הארץ am ha-aretz who was sold to a
חבר, chaveir, כולן צריכין לקבל דברי חבירות. kullan tzerikhin lekabel divrei chavirut.
They have to undergo a formal process of accepting upon themselves formally...
the strictures of what it means to be a חבר. chaver. אבל
אשת חבר שנשאת לעם הארץ, aval eishet chaver sheniseit le'am ha'aretz, but
what about the wife of a חבר chaver who is divorced or
widowed who then marries an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, וכן בתו של חבר שנשאת לעם הארץ, vechein
bito shel chaver sheniseit le'am ha'aretz, וכן עבדו של חבר שנמכר לעם
הארץ, vechein avdo shel chaver shenimkar le'am ha'aretz, but the reverse, they
go from a חבר'ס chaver's household to עם הארץ'ס am ha'aretz's household,
אינן צריכים לקבל דברי חברות לכתחילה, einan tzerichim lekabel divrei chaveirut lechatichila,
דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's opinion is
that they do not need to do any formal process of accepting
חברות chaveirut because we already assume that they're חברים chaverim because that's
the household that they're coming from.
Okay. ורבי יהודה אומר אף הן צריכים לקבל דברי חברות לכתחילה. veRabbi
Yehuda omer af hen tzerichim lekabel divrei chaveirut lechatichila. And he's, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, no, they do need to accept דברי חברות
divrei chaveirut because they've lowered themselves going into the עם הארץ'ס am
ha'aretz's household. וכן היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר. vechein haya Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says מעשה באשה אחת שנשאת לחבר. ma'aseh be'isha achat sheniseit lechaver. There
was a woman who married a חבר, chaver, והייתה קושרת לו תפילין
על ידו, vehayeta kosheret lo tefillin al yado, and then she was
the one who would put the תפילין tefillin on his arm. So,
so that means that she was sort of brought into his household
and was acting according to his ways and everything.
Sorry one sec.
And then למכס, lemoches, and then she married a burglar, someone who
was a thief, הייתה קושרת לו קשרי מוכס על ידו. hayeta kosheret
lo kishrei moches al yado. And then she would tie his burglar's
tools to his arm.
I think I'm by translating this
tax collector.
Tax collector, tax avoider, tax something, something to do with the tax,
right?
מכס meches is a tax, but he's some kind of a, he
was a מוכס moches tax collector, but a strongman tax collector, not
like appropriate taxes, right? So that's why we say more like a
burglar, a thief. So,
so the point is while she was married to the חבר, chaver,
she did like what the חבר chaver did. She put his תפילין
tefillin on for him. And then when she married a tax collector,
so she helped him take the taxes from the Jewish people. So
either way, right, meaning that the woman
is handling תפילין tefillin חס ושלום chas veshalom
but she's helping her husband to put on the תפילין. tefillin. Meaning,
meaning the concern here is that the wife, the wife loves her
husband and she's gonna help him whatever job he has. So whatever
job he's doing, she's gonna assist him with that. That's the assumption.
She rises and falls to his level.
Right, something like that. And again, this is obviously in a time
and with a presumption that a woman doesn't really have an independent
professional identity of any type, she goes along with whatever her husband's
household is doing.
Maybe she knows how to do all the tax collecting too, I
don't know.
There you go, I don't know.
Tax collectors were not כשר. kosher.
Tax collector is not such a good job to do. It's like
being a repo man, it's the same kind of thing.
Well, it was a lot worse in Roman times.
Certainly, because there was a sense that the taxes were unfair and
unjust taxes as well. אמר רב. Amar Rav. So חבית אסור. chavit
assur. So what is חבית? chavit? חבית chavit is a סימן, siman,
חלב בשר יין תכלת. chalav basar yayin techeilet.
Milk, meat, wine, and תכלת. techeilet. Each one of those, רש״י Rashi
tells you the סימן, siman, so those four things אסור בחותם אחד.
assur bechotam echad. They're prohibited if there's only one seal of approval.
That's why often on the כשר kosher meat and things you have
the הכשר hechsher and they say only כשר kosher if the seal
is closed and things like that, right? All these kind of things
because the assumption, what if somebody switched it and they fabricated one
of the seals? So then, then it wouldn't help if it had
a seal. Okay. חמפ״ג מותר בחותם אחד. champag mutar bechotam echad. And
what's חמפ״ג? champag? חמפ״ג champag is
חלתית מורייס פת וגבינה. chiltit muryas pat ugevina. So of a lower
level concern of being adulterated, חלתית chiltit is the asafoetida, מורייס the
fish brine, פת pat bread, and
גבינה gevina cheese. So even things which are all prohibited for rabbinic
reasons, but they have different levels of stringency because of different levels
of concern of how, what's the risk that they'll be adulterated? So
חבית אסור בחותם אחד, chavit assur bechotam echad, חמפ״ג מותר בחותם אחד.
champag mutar bechotam echad. חלב בשר יין תכלת. chalav basar yayin techeilet.
So those four אסורים בחותם אחד. assurim bechotam echad. חלתית מורייס פת
גבינה מותרים בחותם אחד. chiltit muryas pat gevina mutarim bechotam echad. So
פת מאי? pat mai? So we're on the top of לט עמוד
ב, lamed tet amud bet, ל ב? lamed bet? פת למאי ניחוש
לה? pat lemai neichush lah? So what's the concern about bread? What,
what's gonna be mixed with the bread? אי משום איחלופי, im mishum
ichalufi, קרירה בחמימה, kerira bachamima,
if you're gonna mix a hot bread with a cold bread, מידע
ידי, meida yadei, then you'll know. That is if you have a
whole pile of breads, פת ישראל pat Yisrael breads, that were, you
know, had cooled off, and then you sneakily go to the non-Jewish
baker and you take a פת עכו״ם pat akum bread and switch
it with the kosher פת ישראל pat Yisrael bread, but it'll still
be hot cause you just got it from the bakery. So people
will be able to
know. דחיטי דשערי נמי מידע ידי. dechiti desha'ari nami meida yadei. And
if you intermix
wheat breads with barley breads, people also be able to know. אי
כהדדי כיון דאיכא חותם אחד לא טרח ומזייף. ei kahadadi keivan de'ika
chotam echad lo tarach umezayeif. And the point is to interswitch
breads of the same quality, of the same freshness, everything, then people
aren't, cause then if it has a seal, you're not gonna bother
to forge it. not saving any money, right? The point would be
to switch something cheaper for something more expensive to sell for a
profit, but if you're selling the same thing that you got before,
it doesn't matter. So then nobody would waste their time to fabricate
a kosher seal for something that's not going to make them any
money. So that's a good חזקה chazakah to have.
Okay. ורב מה שנא גבינה דלא טרח ומזייף חלב נמי לא טרח
ומזייף? V’rav mah shna gvina delo tarach u’mizaif chalav nami lo tarach
u’mizaif? So what's the difference between cheese and milk? Why does milk
need two seals of כשרות kashrut and cheese only needs one? אמר
רב כהנא אפיק חלב ואייל חתיכת דג שאין בה סימן Amar Rav
Kahana apik chalav ve’ayel chatichat dag she’ein ba siman sorry, אפיק חלב
ואייל חתיכת דג שאין בה סימן. apik chalav ve’ayel chatichat dag she’ein
ba siman. You should replace חלב chalav in the סימן siman actually
with חתיכת דג, chatichat dag, a slice of fish, right? Because the
סימן siman still has the letter ח. chet. So you’re trying to
have a mnemonic but it’s חתיכת דג, chatichat dag, a sliced fish,
a piece of fish that does not have a סימן, siman, that
does not have—this goes back to what I said before about buying
fish that still has the skin on it. If it has the
skin then you can check that it’s a kosher fish. If you
buy a skinned piece of fish you no longer know if it’s
a kosher fish or not. So היינו בשר, haynu basar, but that’s
basically the same הלכה as meat, that is, it’s a piece of
meat I can't look at it and know whether it's kosher or
not, so I have to rely on two signs of proof that
it's kosher. והיינו בשר תרי גווני בשר לא אמרינן, V’haynu basar trei
gavnei basar lo amrinan, two different types of meat, okay fine, don't
worry about it. In the same סימן siman to help you remember
the word חבי"ט chavit is a mnemonic, it's just telling you different
cases. ושמואל אמר בי"ת אסור בחותם אחד. U'shmuel amar bayit assur b'chotam
echad. שמואל has different mnemonics. What is בי"ת bayit and what is
מח"ג מותר בחותם אחד? machag mutar b'chotam echad? בשר יין ותכלת. Basar
yayin tchelet. So he only includes not חבי"ט chavit but בי"ת, bayit,
that
is, ב-י-ת—בשר יין ותכלת אסורים בחותם אחד and מוריס חילתית וגבינה מותרים
בחותם אחד. muryas chiltit v’gvina mutarim b’chotam echad. So שמואל does not
include
the
פת pat in the סימן, siman, he just says מח"ג, machag, not
not חמפ"ג. champag. So that's the difference in his סימן. siman. So
why does he exclude the פת? pat? Because it sounds like the
פת pat concern was not such a real—the bread is a low
risk and also that the fish is basically the same as the
meat, so if bread is not a concern and fish is the
same as meat, so you could have two סימנים simanim of three
letters instead of four letters. So that's the מחלוקת. machloket. Okay. תרי
גווני בשר לא אמרינן. Trei gavnei basar lo amrinan. So you don't
he shouldn't be concerned to include a reference as a דג שאין
בה סימן היינו בשר תרי גווני בשר לא אמרינן, dag she’ein ba
siman haynu basar trei gavnei basar lo amrinan, we don't include two
different examples of the same הלכה in the same סימן. siman. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. The ברייתא baraita says אין לוקחין ימ"ח מח"ג בסוריא.
ein lokchin yamach machag b’suria. So what is ימ"ח yamach and what's—so
ימ"ח yamach is יין מוריס וחלב. yayin muryas v’chalav. One sec, all
these different סימנים. simanim. One
sec. It’s going to be explained in the
גמרא. ימ"ח מח"ג. yamach machag.
Sorry. No, רש"י Rashi doesn't say. What's ימ"ח? yamach? Shmuel, do you
have it expanded in the...
it
says יין מוריס וחלב.
yayin muryas v’chalav. So wine, fish sauce, and milk. And מח"ג machag
then is—but it's also מוריס, muryas, that's why I'm confused...
מלח
מוריס
חלב...
melach muryas
chalav...
no, it's מלח חילתית וגבינה. melach chiltit v’gvina. Okay. Oh right, because
that's the next thing in our משנה is the מלח סנקונדרי. melach
sankundari. Okay. Fine. So it's יין מוריס וחלב, yayin muryas v’chalav, and
then
מלח חילתית וגבינה. melach chiltit v’gvina. So those six בסוריא. b’suria. You
can't purchase them in Syria. לא יין ולא מוריס ולא חלב ולא
מלח סנקונדית ולא חילתית ולא גבינה. Lo yayin v’lo muryas v’lo chalav
v’lo melach sankundit v’lo chiltit v’lo gvina. Those those six. אלא מן
המומחה. Ela min hamumche. You could only purchase them from someone who
is a reputable dealer. וכולם אם נתארח אצל בעל הבית מותר. Vekulam
im nitareach eitzel ba’al habayit mutar. If you're staying at someone's house,
מותר. mutar. Then it’s permissible. That is, you can't buy it except
from someone with a good reputation but if you go to someone's
house, you would be allowed to rely upon it. Does this mean
that you go to someone's house who has a reliable level of
כשרות kashrut or not? That's sort of the question that comes into
a lot of questions nowadays. How much do when you go to
someone's house you start checking all the הכשרים hechsherim and everything in
their cabinets or people have a presumption that they keep kosher. It
varies right, but there are certain people have a mindset like that
or certain people say oh I'll only have the fruit salad, right?
So we have to remember that even for many of these rabbinic
laws the rabbis understood that what they were doing was creating a
stricture and they created mechanisms by which under what circumstances can you
or can you not rely on a presumption that it's kosher, how
much proof do you need, two stamps, one stamp, no stamp at
all, you're at someone's house, you're buying it from the dealer, right?
All of those kind of questions. Okay, מסייע ליה לרבי יהושע בן
לוי. mesaye lei l’Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. It supports רבי יהושע בן
לוי's Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi position, דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי שגר
לו בעל הבית לביתו מותר. d’amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi shagar lo
ba’al habayit l’beito mutar. If someone invites you over to his house,
it's permissible. מאי טעמא בעל הבית לא שביק היתירא ואכיל איסורא. Mai
ta’ama ba’al habayit lo shavek hateira v’achil issura. The בעל הבית... ba’al
habayit... is not going to turn aside the kosher food in order
to eat non-kosher food, וכי משגר ליה ממאי דאכיל משדר ליה, v'chi
meshagar lei mimai d'achil meshadar lei, and the thing that he's eating,
he's also going to serve you. That is, even though there's a
concern that in the marketplace someone might sell something non-kosher to make
a quick buck, but if they're inviting you over to their house
and you know that they keep kosher, then they're going to be
eating the same food as you. And they don't stop eating kosher
just to try to save money on their house guest. So, yeah.
So this sounds like we had something similar
in Talmudic times to the eating טריף treif out.
There was at least a concern about it, so you have to
be worried about it. Obviously they didn't have the same כשרות kashrut
industry we have. They also had many
fewer—their food industry, everything was produced right there. You go to a
fish brine guy, it's this guy and I know him and I've
known him my whole life and he lives down the block from
me. It's also much less of a concern. There was a lot
less money in it. And when there's more money in things, and
you have a restaurant, and you have a wholesaler and a retailer
and everything, there's going to be a lot more problems.
Spices would have come from a long distance potentially though.
Yeah, but spices still, we said the חילתית, chiltit, the problem of
the חילתית chiltit somewhere from India or something. But if we're in
Babylonia, it's not so far. The spice trade or whatever, I don't
know where exactly things come from. Okay, let's try to do the
next little bit of the סוגיא. sugya. We don't really have time.
So we'll do that on שבת Shabbat and we'll try our best
to get caught up. I hope everyone has a great day and
שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom. Sorry about the noise.